A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of F. Champion Ward FA565
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of F. Champion Ward
1953-2002
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ward, F. Champion (1910-2007)
Ford Foundation
FA565
4.03 Cubic Feet 11 Hollinger document boxes
Frederick Champion Ward was born on December 29, 1910 in New Brunswick, New Jersey. In 1954, Dr. Ward took leave from the University of Chicago to travel to India for the Ford Foundation. Upon his return, he joined the Foundation as Director of the Overseas Development Program for the Middle East and Africa. He later became Deputy Vice President for International Programs. In 1965, Dr. Ward was promoted to Vice President of Education and Research, a position he held until 1967 when he became a Program Advisor to International Division's Office of the Vice President. He retired from the Foundation in 1977. The office files of Dr. C.F. Ward span from 1956 to 2002, although the bulk of the files date prior to 1978. The collection describes Dr. Ward's areas of responsibility within the Ford Foundation, including education in Latin America and development in Asia and the Pacific as well as the Middle East and Africa.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation established the Overseas Development Program, one of its first grant programs, in 1951. Its granting goals were to increase agricultural production, improve health and living conditions, and advance education. India and Pakistan were the focus of the initial grants, with a more limited number of grants issued in Indonesia and Burma. A program for smaller regional and national grants was initiated for the Near East region later the same year.
As part of a Foundation reorganization in 1966, the Overseas Development Program, along with other international Foundation programs such as International Training and Research and Population, became part of a unified International Division. Following another Foundation reorganization in 1983, the International Division was eliminated and two program divisions were created—the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) and Developing Countries Program (DCP).
Biographical / Historical
Frederick Champion Ward was born on December 29, 1910 in New Brunswick, New Jersey. He graduated from Oberlin College in 1932 and was awarded a master's in philosophy in 1935. He went on to earn a doctorate in philosophy from Yale in 1937. He taught philosophy and psychology from 1937 to 1945 at Denison University and, as Associate Dean, trained military officers for de-Nazification efforts in postwar Germany. After the war, Dr. Ward joined the faculty of the University of Chicago and served as Dean of the undergraduate Humanities Division from 1947 to 1954.
In 1954, Dr. Ward took leave from the university to travel to India for the Ford Foundation. Upon his return, he joined the Foundation as Director of the Overseas Development Program for the Middle East and Africa. He later became Deputy Vice President for International Programs. In 1965, he was promoted to Vice President of Education and Research, a position he held until 1967 when he became a Program Advisor to International Division's Office of the Vice President. He retired from the Foundation in 1977.
During the 1960s Dr. Ward served as Chairman of the White House Task Force on the Education of Gifted Persons and was a member of the UNESCO International Commission on the Development of Education.
After his retirement from the Foundation, Dr. Ward worked as a consultant for the World Bank, the Association of American Universities, and the Connecticut Board of Education. From 1978 to 1981, he was a senior consultant to the Board of the MacArthur Foundation and helped establish the "genius grant." Dr. Ward also served as Chancellor of the New School for Social Research in Manhattan from 1980 to 1983. He died on July 2, 2007 at the age of 96.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into 3 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Subject Files, 1953-2002
Series II. Ward's Words, 1963-1977
Series III. Writings, 1985
Scope and Contents
The office files of Dr. F. Champion Ward span from 1956 to 2002, although the bulk predate 1978. Topics covered in the collection reflect his areas of responsibility, including education in Latin America and development in Asia and the Pacific. Other files pertain to the Foundation's educational grant-making in the Middle East and Africa.
Dr. Ward's files on Asia and the Pacific document the Ford Foundation's role in supporting both regional education programs overseas and Asian studies programs in the United States. His "Asia and Pacific Concerns" files include reports on the Foundation's work in India and Japan as well as grants to establish libraries in Asia. Also included are documents pertaining to a 1975 visit to India by members of the Board of Trustees. There are also files about the Foundation's support for the Asian studies program at the University of Chicago. The files for the Middle East and Africa contain memoranda describing Foundation grant activities in Ghana, Jordan and Turkey.
The files on the Southeast Asian Fellowship Program (SAFP) reveal the Foundation's response to geopolitical developments, particularly after the fall of Saigon in 1975. The Ford Foundation had been supporting educational development in South Vietnam prior to 1975. After the fall of Saigon, the Foundation established the SAFP to provide temporary support for forty-two displaced scholars and intellectuals from Cambodia and Vietnam. In addition, the files for Vietnam contain correspondence that further documents the Foundation's actions prior to and following the fall of Saigon.
Related Materials
FA547 Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of Forrest F. Hill contains additional information about the Overseas Development program. Dr. Hill served as Vice President of Overseas Development for the Ford Foundation and worked closely with Dr. Ward.
Later office files of Forrest F. Hill were partially intermingled with some of Dr. Ward's office files and cover related subjects.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Subject Files, 1953-2002; I; 3.27 Cubic Feet 9 letter document boxes and 1 half-legal box
  Scope and Contents
  Dr. Ward kept subject files for Ford Foundation grantees and grant projects and for Foundation policy developments. Other files concern matters of the Board of Trustees. Of note are the files on Vietnam, which detail the Foundation's grant work in South Vietnam as well as policy changes instituted after the fall of Saigon.
  Arrangement
  Alphabetical
  - Afghanistan Trip -- Notes and Memoranda Re: Research Project in Afghanistan, 1978 March (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agency for International Development (AID) -- Memoranda Re: Education Grants, Background, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Council on Education -- Correspondence and Meeting Minutes Re: Presidential Initiatives, 1977 February 7-April 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Asia and Pacific Concerns -- Memoranda Re: East Asian Libraries, South Asian Studies, Thai October Revolution, etc. (1 of 4), 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Asia and Pacific Concerns -- Reports on India, Japan, Economic Review, etc. (2 of 4), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Asia and Pacific Concerns -- Notes and Memoranda Re: South Asian Education, etc. (3 of 4), 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Asia and Pacific Concerns -- Reports and Correspondence Re: Trustees in India, etc. (4 of 4), 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Asia and Pacific -- Sri Lanka (Ceylon) -- Memoranda Re: Meetings, etc., 1956-1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Asia and Pacific -- Thailand - Memoranda Re: Meeting, etc., 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Asian Development Bank -- Report on Bank's Role in Education, 1970 March (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Asian Studies -- Columbia -- Expenditures, Notes, Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Asian Studies -- Cornell -- Reports, Correspondence, Expenditures, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Asian Studies -- Harvard -- Notes, Expenditures, Memoranda Re: Site Visit, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Asian Studies -- University of California, Berkeley -- Report and Expenditures, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Asian Studies -- University of Chicago -- South Asian Studies -- Report, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Asian Studies -- University of Chicago -- Financing, Proposal, Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Asian Studies -- University of Chicago -- Grant Reports, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Asian Studies -- University of Michigan -- Notes, Background, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Assistance to Education in the '70s" -- Manuscript and Comments, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Board of Trustees Docket, 1975 June 26-27 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chile Trip -- Memoranda, Reports, Transcripts Re: Education, Notes, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cultural Grants -- Memoranda Re: Policy on Overseas Grants, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cummings, William K. -- Correspondence Re: Appointment, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Education -- Meeting Agenda, Reports, Memoranda, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Education -- Memoranda Re: Program Strategy, etc., 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Education -- Memoranda -- Dr. Reuben Frodin, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Education and World Affairs (EWA) -- F. Champion Ward's Personal Files, 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Education Group -- Meetings -- Agenda, Memoranda, Background, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Education Group -- Retrospective Language Survey -- Education Conference, Survey Background Documents (1 of 2), 1973 January-November (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Education Group -- Retrospective Language Survey -- Higher Education Study, Consultant Reports (2 of 2), 1973 December-1974 February (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Educational Development Corporation (EDC) -- Memorandum from Francis X. Sutton Re: EDC Study of Kenya's Educational System, 1970 March 11 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Endowment Grants -- Guidelines -- Memorandum, 1976 February 9 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Evaluation -- Meeting Information on University Grant Evaluations, 1973 January 5-17 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Gordon, Shirley -- Universidade Federal da Bahia -- Correspondence and Proposal Re: FF Project Specialist, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - India Ministry of Education -- Correspondence, Reports, 1956-2002 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Institute of International Education (IIE) -- Memoranda, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - International Association for Cultural Freedom -- Memoranda Re: Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD) -- Re: External Evaluation of IBRD's Education Program, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - International Council for Educational Development (ICED) -- Grantee Report, Handwritten Notes, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - International Division Conference, New Delhi, India -- Operation Janus, 1961-1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - International Division Meeting -- Rapporteur's Reports, 1975 September 19-23 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - International Institute of Educational Research (IIER) -- Memoranda Re: Organization Plans, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - International Studies Review -- Memoranda, Reports, Notes on Grant Evaluations (1 of 3), 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - International Studies Review -- Memoranda, Reports, Notes (2 of 3), 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - International Studies Review -- Memoranda, Reports, Notes (3 of 3), 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - International Studies Review -- ACLS/SSRC -- Notes and Memoranda Re: Committees, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - International Studies Review -- OE/ACE/IEP -- Memoranda, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - LAC -- Mexico -- Separated Reports, Address Change, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda -- Re: ICED, CIDA, Teacher Training, etc. (1 of 2), 1971 February-April (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda -- Re: UNESCO, Canada Visits, etc. (2 of 2), 1971 July-1972 January (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - MEA -- East and Central Africa -- Memoranda Re: Grants, Meetings, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - MEA -- Ghana -- FF Activities Resume, 1961-1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - MEA -- Jordon -- Arab Development Society Memoranda, 1962-1966 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - MEA -- Turkey -- Reports (separated), 1953-1957 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Minnesota, University of -- Site Visit Report, 1975 February 14 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - New York/Regional -- Proposals for SEA Grants, Pakistan Close-Out, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Nuclear Power Issues: A Foundation Strategy" (report), 1975 June (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Pakistan -- Correspondence Re: FF Support, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Personnel Recruiting -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Project Specialist for Indonesia, 1978 January 17-July 20 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Planning, Exploration and Evaluation at FF -- Memoranda and Discussion Papers on Grant Evaluations, 1969-1975 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Pontifical Catholic University of Chile -- Foundation Concerns -- Report, Correspondence, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Pontifical Catholic University of Chile -- Notes and Proposals (some in Spanish), 1968 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Population Council -- Memorandum Re: Financing, 1964 January 4 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Program Planning -- Memoranda, Discussion Paper, 1972-1977 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Project 87 -- Re: Grant for Constitutional Research, 1978 May (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Public Policy Committee -- Proposals, Meeting Agenda, Minutes, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Representatives Meeting -- Notes and Meeting Materials, 1977 March (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - SEAMEO (Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Organization) -- Memorandum Re: Paul Hanna Visit, 1971 May 7 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - SAFP (Southeast Asia Fellowship Program) -- Awardees, Forms, PR Information, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - SAFP -- Bliatout, Thowpaou, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - SAFP -- Nguyen, Cong An, 1975 August 8-12 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - SAFP -- Nguyen, Dinh Hoan, 1975 July 11-24 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - SAFP -- Nguyen, Hai Binh -- Correspondence, 1975 July 24-August 5 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - SAFP -- Nguyen, Mong Bich -- Correspondence, 1975 August 12 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - SAFP -- Nguyen, Thanh Hai, 1975 August 7-14 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - SAFP -- Phan, Vu Trong, 1975 July 31-August 11 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Social Sciences in Asia -- Program Papers, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Stanford University -- Asian Studies Grant Reports (1 of 3), 1975 March (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Stanford University -- Asian Studies Grant Reports (2 of 3), 1975 June (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Stanford University -- Asian Studies Grant Reports (3 of 3), 1975 July (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Trustee Project Papers -- Staff Papers for Trustee Planning Project on International Activities (1 of 2), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Trustee Project Papers -- Staff Papers for Trustee Planning Project on International Activities (2 of 2), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Meetings, Proposal, 1957-1966 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - University of Pennsylvania International Training Grants -- Correspondence, Proposals, Reports and Memoranda Re: FF Grants to UPenn, 1960-1975 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Vietnam -- FF Correspondence and Reports on Education Grants, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Vietnam -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Fall of South Vietnam and FF, 1975-1977 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Washington Activity -- Memorandum Re: International Education, 1977 February 11 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - World Bank -- Memoranda Re: International Education, Background, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Ward's Words, 1963-1977; II; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  The documents that comprise this series had been stored in three expandable folders which were labeled "Ward's Words." The papers, memoranda and other miscellaneous documents appear to have been gathered by Dr. Ward or a colleague for reference purposes. Many but not all of the documents were written by or sent to Dr. Ward. The original chronological arrangement was retained. Within yearly increments, the files have been arranged by subject.
  - Address -- "An Exile's Report" by F. Champion Ward, 1976 February 23 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "A Note on Knowing, Acting, Making and the College Curriculum" by F. Champion Ward, 1970 August 12 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Aspen College" by F. Champion Ward, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Bellagio Meetings Re: Education, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Bellagio Meetings Re: Education Policy Development, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Board of Trustees Education Paper, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Education Group -- Memoranda, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Education Paper -- Assistance to Education in the 1970s and Related Memoranda, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Education Reference Papers, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Educational Resource Bases -- FF Support for International Education -- Memoranda and Correspondence, Trip Reports, 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Field Office Educational Development Dissenting Responses, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "Future Program Choices in Education and Research", 1975 March (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Ghana Case Study, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - International Bureau of Education -- Assessment and Correspondence Re: Asian Education, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - IDRC Task Force -- Reports, Memoranda Re: Women's Education in Developing Nations (1 of 2), 1975 February-March (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - IDRC Task Force -- Meeting Agenda, Reports (2 of 2), 1975 April-August (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Meeting Agenda -- Field Offices, 1970 June (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Meeting to Plan Division-Wide Conference of Education Advisors, 1975 January 10 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous -- Bellagio Meeting Memoranda, etc., 1975 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Projects -- Memoranda Re: Grant Report, Research Group, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Schedule -- Dacca Trip, 1977 January 11 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Trip and Meeting Reports -- India League Award to FF, Geneva Visit, 1975 September 12-October 17 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Trip Reports -- Visits to Asia, India, Indonesia, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Writings, 1985; III; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - Memoirs by F. Champion Ward, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 10)